<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>org.gitfourchette.gitfourchette</id>
  <name>GitFourchette</name>
  <developer_name>Iliyas Jorio</developer_name>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0</project_license>

  <provides><id>org.gitfourchette.gitfourchette.desktop</id></provides>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.gitfourchette.gitfourchette.desktop</launchable>

  <summary>The comfortable Git UI</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr">L’interface Git tout confort</summary>

  <description>
    <p>Explore your repos easily. Craft commits intuitively. GitFourchette will become your new home to get work done in your Git repositories.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">Explorez vos dépôts facilement. Créez vos commits intuitivement. Vous vous sentirez comme chez vous dans GitFourchette pour accomplir toutes vos tâches dans vos dépôts Git.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>A comfortable way to explore and understand your Git repositories</li>
      <li xml:lang="fr">Une manière conviviale d’explorer et de comprendre vos dépôts Git</li>

      <li>Powerful tools to stage code, create commits, and manage branches</li>
      <li xml:lang="fr">Des outils puissants pour indexer du code, créer des commits, et gérer vos branches</li>

      <li>Snappy and intuitive Qt UI designed to fit in snugly with KDE Plasma</li>
      <li xml:lang="fr">Une interface Qt réactive et intuitive, pensée pour bien s’intégrer dans KDE Plasma</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <url type="homepage">https://gitfourchette.org</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/issues</url>
  <url type="help">https://gitfourchette.org/guide</url>
  <url type="donation">https://ko-fi.com/jorio</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette</url>
  <url type="translate">https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette-private/blob/master/gitfourchette/assets/lang/README.md</url>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#bad6f0</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#1d4264</color>
  </branding>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://gitfourchette.org/_static/appstream/packshot-shadow-light.png</image>
      <caption>Exploring a repository in GitFourchette (light mode).</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="fr">Exploration d’un dépôt dans GitFourchette (mode clair).</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://gitfourchette.org/_static/appstream/packshot-shadow-dark.png</image>
      <caption>Exploring a repository in GitFourchette (dark mode).</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="fr">Exploration d’un dépôt dans GitFourchette (mode sombre).</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <categories>
    <category>Development</category>
    <category>RevisionControl</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>git</keyword>
    <keyword>qt</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <releases>
    <release version="1.3.0" date="2025-05-03" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.3.0</url>
      <description>
        <p><em>Upgrade note:</em> The terminal command template now requires the <code>$COMMAND</code> argument placeholder. Please review your terminal command in <em>Settings → External Tools → Terminal</em>.</p>
        <p>New features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Custom terminal commands (Settings → Custom Commands) (#37).</li>
        <li>Sidebar: Hide All But This (#49). You can now show a single branch and hide all others.</li>
        <li>Add file to .gitignore or .git/info/exclude from untracked file context menu (#42)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>GraphView: Conjoined refboxes when a local branch is in sync with its upstream (#12)</li>
        <li>Add target branch shorthand to default merge commit message (#39)</li>
        <li>NewBranchDialog: Pre-tick upstream checkbox if branching off remote branch</li>
        <li>Report mandatory placeholder token errors when launching external tool commands</li>
        <li>Speed up remote listing and upstream lookup</li>
        <li>Fix Sidebar/DiffArea would sometimes jump around by a few pixels while temporary banners were shown</li>
        <li>Override Yaru icon theme's "scary" red warning icon (#27)</li>
        <li>More helpful message if Python bindings for QtSvg are missing</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Sidebar: Strip initial slash in nested RefFolder display names (#45)</li>
        <li>Fix Ctrl+G keyboard shortcut on GNOME</li>
        <li>Work around window snapping issue on GNOME (#50)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Two other bug fixes originally introduced in v1.2.0 had been dormant until now due to depending on a pygit2 version bump – they are now in full effect:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix push progress wasn't reported properly during transfer (requires pygit2 1.18.0) (#22)</li>
        <li>Fix push couldn't be canceled once the transfer starts (requires pygit2 1.18.0) (#22)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.1" date="2025-03-05" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.2.1</url>
      <description>
        <p>User-suggested quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>GraphView: Copy commit message from context menu (#33)</li>
        <li>Rephrase some messages (diff too large, delete untracked file) (#27, #28)</li>
        <li>Add Ptyxis terminal preset (#18)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Other quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Friendlier messages related to 'autocrlf' and 'safecrlf' options (#30)</li>
        <li>Flatpak distribution: Detach terminal process from application</li>
        <li>Improve contrast between enabled/disabled SVG icons throughout the UI</li>
        <li>Pasting a multiline commit message into CommitDialog's summary input box will correctly split the message across the summary and description boxes</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix error when an external program converts line endings in the workdir with 'autocrlf' (#30)</li>
        <li>Flatpak distribution: Fix terminal spawned in incorrect working directory (#18)</li>
        <li>Flatpak distribution: Fix Flatpak tool existence check</li>
        <li>Gracefully handle destruction of parent widget of external tool processes</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.2.0" date="2025-02-19" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.2.0</url>
      <description>
        <p>New features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Open terminal in workdir (#18)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>User-suggested quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Reword "Uncommitted changes" to "Working directory" to clear up any confusion when there are no changes (#13)</li>
        <li>Always display the number of uncommitted changes in the sidebar and in the graph; update this whenever the app returns to the foreground (#13)</li>
        <li>Reword "Discard Changes" context menu entry for untracked files to "Delete File" (#17)</li>
        <li>Global ref sorting setting (#20)</li>
        <li>Allow creating a merge commit without fast-forwarding (#21)</li>
        <li>Dark mode readability tweaks (#24)</li>
        <li>Command line: Open arbitrary nested paths in a repo (#25)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Other quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Improve consistency of ellipses in menus to signify that an action can be canceled</li>
        <li>Warn user if an external Flatpak isn't installed when attempting to run it (merge tool, terminals, etc.)</li>
        <li>Remind user about any unstaged files when about to create an empty commit</li>
        <li>Allow middle-clicking to quickly stage/unstage selected lines in DiffView (enable in Settings → Advanced → Middle-click)</li>
        <li>Allow clearing draft commit messages by right-clicking the top row in GraphView</li>
        <li>After pushing a branch that doesn't track an upstream, PushDialog will suggest the remote branch you used previously (instead of defaulting to the first one in the repo)</li>
        <li>Pulling will automatically fast-forward if possible without an extra confirmation step, unless your git config contains "pull.ff=false" (behavior aligned to vanilla git). If fast-forwarding isn't possible, you will still be prompted to merge.</li>
        <li>Push/fetch status text uses the 'tnum' OpenType feature to avoid transfer rate numbers jumping around if your system font has digits with uneven widths</li>
        <li>AppImage distribution now compatible with fuse3</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix crash when closing several repos in quick succession, e.g. by holding down Ctrl+W</li>
        <li>Fix clicking the help button used to close the fast-forward dialog</li>
        <li>Fix DiffView out of sync with rest of RepoWidget after hiding a the currently-selected branch tip</li>
        <li>Fix italics in sidebar didn't update after changing the current branch's upstream (a remote-tracking branch in italics means it's the upstream for the current branch)</li>
        <li>Fix visual artifacts around character-level diffs in DiffView</li>
        <li>Fix push progress wasn't reported properly during transfer (requires pygit2 1.18.0) (#22)</li>
        <li>Fix push couldn't be canceled once the transfer starts (requires pygit2 1.18.0) (#22)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Breaking changes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>The keyboard shortcut for "Go to Working Directory" is now Ctrl+G (formerly Ctrl+U, for "Uncommitted Changes"). On most keyboard layouts, Ctrl+G pairs nicely with Ctrl+H for "Go to HEAD".</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.1" date="2025-01-19" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.1.1</url>
      <description>
        <p>New features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Option to remember passphrases in encrypted keyfiles (#15)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Omit remote name from refboxes when there's just 1 remote (#11)</li>
        <li>Display blob hashes in FileList tooltips</li>
        <li>GraphView tries to use the 'tnum' OpenType feature to align ISO-8601 dates if your system font has digits with uneven widths</li>
        <li>In commit/filename SearchBars, don't re-trigger a search if appending to a word that is known to have no occurrences</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix custom key file feature in CloneDialog and AddRemote</li>
        <li>Fix remote branch context menu in a repo with an unborn head</li>
        <li>GraphSplicer: Fix discrete branch may vanish from graph if moved past another branch by topological sorting</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.0" date="2025-01-05" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.1.0</url>
      <description>
        <p>New features:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Syntax highlighting with Pygments (optional dependency)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Customizable ref indicator width (Settings → Commit History) (#10)</li>
        <li>Condensed fonts can be disabled (Settings → Advanced) (#10)</li>
        <li>Improved settings dialog UI</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.2" date="2024-12-16" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.0.2</url>
      <description>
        <p>Usability improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Support launching a Flatpak as an external diff/merge tool (#4)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix web URLs in remote-tracking branch context menus (e.g. visit a branch on github.com)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.1" date="2024-12-03" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.0.1</url>
      <description>
        <p>Quality of life improvements:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Friendlier ConflictView UI</li>
        <li>Improve 3-way merging with external merge tools when there's no ancestor in the conflict</li>
        <li>Distinguish submodules and subtrees in SpecialDiff verbiage</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Bug fixes:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix discarding untracked non-submodule subtrees (#1)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.0" date="2024-11-16" type="stable">
      <url>https://github.com/jorio/gitfourchette/releases/tag/v1.0.0</url>
      <description>
        <ul>
        <li>First public release</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
